Today I'm going to talk to you about the problem of other minds.
اليوم أنا سأتكلّم معكم عن مشكلة العقول الأخرى .
And the problem I'm going to talk about
و المشكلة التي سأتكلّم عليها
is not the familiar one from philosophy,
ليست المألوفة من الفلسفة ،
which is, "How can we know
التي هي ،" كيف نستطيع أن نعرف
whether other people have minds?"
إذا ما كان النّاس الآخرون لديهم عقول ؟"
That is, maybe you have a mind,
ذلك ، ربّما لديك عقل ،
and everyone else is just a really convincing robot.
و كلّ شخص آخر هو فقط روبوتا مقنعا فعلاً .
So that's a problem in philosophy,
إذن هذه مشكلة في الفلسفة .
but for today's purposes I'm going to assume
لكنّ لأغراض اليوم أنا سأفترض
that many people in this audience have a mind,
أنّ أناس كثيرة في هذا الجمهور لديها عقل ،
and that I don't have to worry about this.
و أنّه لا يجب عليّ أن أقلق على هذا .
There is a second problem that is maybe even more familiar to us
هناك مشكلة ثانية ربّما نحن معتادون عليها
as parents and teachers and spouses
كآباء و مدرّسين و زوجات،
and novelists,
و روائيّون .
which is, "Why is it so hard
الذي هي ، لماذا هو صعب جدًّا
to know what somebody else wants or believes?"
أن تعرف ما يريده شخص ما آخر أو ما يؤمن به ؟ "
Or perhaps, more relevantly,
أو ربّما ، على نحو متّصل بالموضوع أكثر ،
"Why is it so hard to change what somebody else wants or believes?"
"لماذا هو صعب جدًّا أن تغيّر ما يريده شخص آخر أو إعتقاده ؟"
I think novelists put this best.
أعتقد أنّ الرّوائيّين وضعوا هذا الأفضل .
Like Philip Roth, who said,
مثل فيليب روث الّذي قال ،
"And yet, what are we to do about this terribly significant business
" و حتّى الآن ، ماذا نفعل مع هذه الأعمال الصعبة للغاية
of other people?
للناس الآخرين؟
So ill equipped are we all,
إذن نحن كلنا غير مجهزين لذلك ،
to envision one another's interior workings
لتصوّر أنّ أفكار شخص ما الداخلية
and invisible aims."
وأهداف غير مرئيّة ".
So as a teacher and as a spouse,
مثلا كمدرّسة، و كزوجة ،
this is, of course, a problem I confront every day.
هذه هي، بالطّبع ، مشكلة أواجهها يوميًّا .
But as a scientist, I'm interested in a different problem of other minds,
لكنّي كعالمة ، أنا مهتمّة بمسألة مختلفة للعقول الأخرى ،
and that is the one I'm going to introduce to you today.
وتلك المسألة هى التي سأقدمها لكم اليوم .
And that problem is, "How is it so easy
و تلك المشكلة هى ،"كم هو سهل جدًّا
to know other minds?"
أن تعرف العقول الأخرى ؟ "
So to start with an illustration,
لنبدأ بعرض توضيح ،
you need almost no information,
لا تحتاج تقريبًا لأى معلومات ،
one snapshot of a stranger,
صورة واحدة لشخص غريب ،
to guess what this woman is thinking,
لتّخمين في ما تفكّر فيه هذه المرأة ،
or what this man is.
أو هذا الرّجل .
And put another way, the crux of the problem is
و بوضع طريقة أخرى ، يكون لبّ المشكلة
the machine that we use for thinking about other minds,
الماكينة الّتي نستخدمها للتّفكير في العقول الأخرى ،
our brain, is made up of pieces, brain cells,
عقلنا ، مكوّن من قطع ، خلايا المخّ ،
that we share with all other animals, with monkeys
التي تماثل كلّ الحيوانات الأخرى ، مع القرود،
and mice and even sea slugs.
و الفئران ، و حتى الرخويات البحرية .
And yet, you put them together in a particular network,
و حتّى الآن ، نضعهم جميعا في شبكة خاصّة ،
and what you get is the capacity to write Romeo and Juliet.
و ما تحصل عليه هو القدرة لتكتب روميو و جولييت .
Or to say, as Alan Greenspan did,
أو للقول، كما فعل آلان جرينسبان،
"I know you think you understand what you thought I said,
"أعرف أنكم تعتقدون أنّكم تفهمون ما اعتقدتم أننيّ قلت ،
but I'm not sure you realize that what you heard
لكننيّ غير متأكّدة أنكم أدركتم ما سمعتموه
is not what I meant."
ليس ما عنيته ".
(Laughter)
(ضحك )
So, the job of my field of cognitive neuroscience
لذا عملى في حقل علم الأعصاب الإدراكى
is to stand with these ideas,
هو أن تقف بهذه الأفكار،
one in each hand.
واحد في كلّ يد .
And to try to understand how you can put together
و لمحاولة الفهم كيف يمكن أن تجمّع
simple units, simple messages over space and time, in a network,
الوحدات البسيطة، الرّسائل البسيطة على المكان و الوقت، في شبكة،
and get this amazing human capacity to think about minds.
وتحصل على هذه النتيجة الرائعة لكيفية تفكير الإنسان في العقول .
So I'm going to tell you three things about this today.
لذا أنا سأخبركم ثلاثة أشياء عن هذا اليوم .
Obviously the whole project here is huge.
من الواضح أن المشروع بالكامل هنا ضخم .
And I'm going to tell you just our first few steps
و أنا سأخبركم فقط أوّل خطوات قليلة
about the discovery of a special brain region
عن اكتشاف منطقة خاصة في المخّ
for thinking about other people's thoughts.
للتّفكير في أفكار النّاس الأخرى .
Some observations on the slow development of this system
بعض الملاحظات على التطوير البطيء لهذا النّظام
as we learn how to do this difficult job.
بينما نتعلّم كيف نعمل هذا العمل الصّعب .
And then finally, to show that some of the differences
ثمّ أخيرًا، لإظهار بعض من الاختلافات
between people, in how we judge others,
بين النّاس، في كيفية الحكم على الآخرين،
can be explained by differences in this brain system.
يمكن أن يُشْرَح بالاختلافات في نظام المخّ هذا .
So first, the first thing I want to tell you is that
إذن أوّلا، الشّيء الأوّل الذي أريد إخباركم هو أنه
there is a brain region in the human brain, in your brains,
هناك منطقة مخّ في العقل البشريّ ، في عقولكم ،
whose job it is to think about other people's thoughts.
عملها هو التّفكير في أفكار الناس الآخرين .
This is a picture of it.
هذه صورة لها .
It's called the Right Temporo-Parietal Junction.
تُسَمَّى وصلة تيمبورو- باريتال اليمنى .
It's above and behind your right ear.
إنّه فوق وخلف أذنكم اليمنى .
And this is the brain region you used when you saw the pictures I showed you,
و هذه هي منطقة المخّ الّتي استخدمتموها عندما رأيتم الصّور التي أظهرتها لكم ،
or when you read Romeo and Juliet
أو عندما تقرأون روميو و جولييت ،
or when you tried to understand Alan Greenspan.
أو عندما حاولتم فهم آلان جرينسبان .
And you don't use it for solving any other kinds of logical problems.
و لا تستخدموه لحلّ أيّ نوع من الأنواع الأخرى للمشاكل المنطقيّة .
So this brain region is called the Right TPJ.
لذا منطقة المخّ هذه تُسَمَّى آر تي بي جيه .
And this picture shows the average activation
وتظهر هذه الصورة متوسط النشاط
in a group of what we call typical human adults.
في مجموعة ما نسمّيه نماذج بالغين بشريّين .
They're MIT undergraduates.
هم جامعيّون فى معهد مساشوستس للتكنولوجيا .
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
The second thing I want to say about this brain system
الشّيء الثّاني الذي أريد أن أقوله عن نظام المخّ هذا
is that although we human adults
هو أنه بالرّغم من أننا أشخاص بالغون
are really good at understanding other minds,
وجيّدون فعلاً في تفهم العقول الأخرى ،
we weren't always that way.
لم نكن دائمًا بهذه الطّريقة .
It takes children a long time to break into the system.
الأطفال يأخذون وقت طويل للدخول فى هذا النظام .
I'm going to show you a little bit of that long, extended process.
سأريكم قليلا من تلك العمليّة الطويلة , الممتدّة الإجراءات .
The first thing I'm going to show you is a change between age three and five,
الشيء الأول الذي سأوضحه لكم هو تغيير بين سنْ الثالثة و الخامسة ،
as kids learn to understand
بينما يتعلّم الأطفال الفهم
that somebody else can have beliefs that are different from their own.
أنّه يمكن أن يكون لدى شخص ما معتقدات مختلفة عن خاصته .
So I'm going to show you a five-year-old
لذا سأعرض لكم طفل بالغ من العمر خمسة سنوات
who is getting a standard kind of puzzle
معه نوع معين من الألعاب
that we call the false belief task.
التي نسميها مهمّة المعتقد الخاطئ .
Rebecca Saxe (Video): This is the first pirate. His name is Ivan.
الفيديو : هذا هو القرصان الأوّل . اسمه إيفان .
And you know what pirates really like?
و تعرفون ماذا يحبون القراصنة ؟
Child: What? RS: Pirates really like cheese sandwiches.
يحب القراصنة فعلاً ساندوتشات الجبن .
Child: Cheese? I love cheese!
الطّفل : الجبن ؟ أحبّ الجبن !
RS: Yeah. So Ivan has this cheese sandwich,
آر . إس . : نعم . لذا إيفان لديه ساندوتش الجبن هذا .
and he says, "Yum yum yum yum yum!
و يقول " يوم يوم يوم يوم يوم !
I really love cheese sandwiches."
أنا أحبّ ساندوتشات الجبن فعلاً ".
And Ivan puts his sandwich over here, on top of the pirate chest.
و يضع إيفان ساندوتشه ها هنا ، فوق صدر القرصان .
And Ivan says, "You know what? I need a drink with my lunch."
و إيفان يقول ، " تعرف ماذا ؟ أحتاج لشراب مع غدائي ."
And so Ivan goes to get a drink.
و لذا إيفان يذهب ليحضر شراب .
And while Ivan is away
و بينما يكون إيفان بعيدًا
the wind comes,
تهب الرّيح،
and it blows the sandwich down onto the grass.
و تأخذ السّاندوتش إلي أسفل على العشب .
And now, here comes the other pirate.
و الآن، هنا يجيء القرصان الآخر .
This pirate is called Joshua.
هذا القرصان يُسَمَّى جوشوا .
And Joshua also really loves cheese sandwiches.
وجاشوا يحبّ فعلاً ساندوتشات الجبن .
So Joshua has a cheese sandwich and he says,
لذا جاشوا لديه ساندوتش جبن و يقول،
"Yum yum yum yum yum! I love cheese sandwiches."
"يوم يوم يوم يوم يوم ! أحبّ ساندوتشات الجبن ".
And he puts his cheese sandwich over here on top of the pirate chest.
و يضع ساندوتش جبنه ها هنا فوق صدر القرصان .
Child: So, that one is his.
الطّفل : إذن ، إن ذلك ملكه .
RS: That one is Joshua's. That's right.
آر . إس . : ذلك الساندوتش ملك جاشوا . هذا صحيح .
Child: And then his went on the ground.
الطفل : وساندوتشه وقع على الأرض .
RS: That's exactly right.
آر . إس . : ذلك صحيح بالضّبط .
Child: So he won't know which one is his.
الطّفل : لذا لن يعرف أيّ واحد ملكه .
RS: Oh. So now Joshua goes off to get a drink.
آر . إس . : آه . الآن جاشوا ذهب لإحضار شراب
Ivan comes back and he says, "I want my cheese sandwich."
يعود إيفان و يقول ، "أريد ساندوتش الجبنة خاصتى ".
So which one do you think Ivan is going to take?
لذا أيّ واحد تعتقدون أنّ إيفان سيأخذ ؟
Child: I think he is going to take that one.
الطّفل : أعتقد أنه سيأخذ ذلك .
RS: Yeah, you think he's going to take that one? All right. Let's see.
آر . إس . : نعم ، تعتقد أنه سيأخذ ذلك ؟حسنًا . دعنا نرى .
Oh yeah, you were right. He took that one.
آه نعم، أنت كنت صحيحًا . أخذ ذلك الساندوتش .
So that's a five-year-old who clearly understands
إذن طفل بالغ من العمر خمسة سنوات يفهم بوضوح
that other people can have false beliefs
أنه لدى الناس الأخرى معتقدات خاطئة
and what the consequences are for their actions.
و ما العواقب لأفعالهم .
Now I'm going to show you a three-year-old
الآن سأريكم طفل بالغ من العمر ثلاثة سنوات
who got the same puzzle.
سنعطيه نفس اللعبة .
RS: And Ivan says, "I want my cheese sandwich."
الفيديو : آر . إس . : و إيفان يقول ، "أريد ساندوتشى الجبني ".
Which sandwich is he going to take?
أيّ السّاندوتشات سيأخذ هو ؟
Do you think he's going to take that one? Let's see what happens.
هل تعتقد أنه سيأخذ ذلك ؟ دعنا نرى ماذا يحدث .
Let's see what he does. Here comes Ivan.
دعنا نرى ما يعمله . هنا يجيء إيفان .
And he says, "I want my cheese sandwich."
و يقول، "أريد ساندوتشى الجبنة ".
And he takes this one.
و يأخذ هذا الساندوتش .
Uh-oh. Why did he take that one?
أه-أوه . لماذا أخذ ذلك ؟
Child: His was on the grass.
الطّفل : كان خاصته على العشب .
So the three-year-old does two things differently.
آر . إس . لذا الطفل البالغ من العمر ثلاثة سنوات يفعل شيئين مختلفين .
First, he predicts Ivan will take the sandwich
أوّلاً يتنبّأ أنّ إيفان سيأخذ السّاندوتش
that's really his.
الذي يخصه بالفعل .
And second, when he sees Ivan taking the sandwich where he left his,
وثانيا ، عندما يرى إيفان يأخذ السّاندوتش حيث ترك خاصته فى مكانه ،
where we would say he's taking that one because he thinks it's his,
حيث سنقول أنه يأخذ ذلك الساندوتش لأنه يعتقد أنّه ملكه ،
the three-year-old comes up with another explanation:
الطفل البالغ من العمر ثلاثة سنوات يتوصّل إلى تفسير آخر .
He's not taking his own sandwich because he doesn't want it,
لا يأخذ ساندوتشه الخاص به لأنه لا يريده ،
because now it's dirty, on the ground.
لأنه الآن هو مُتسخ ، على الأرض .
So that's why he's taking the other sandwich.
لذلك يفسر لماذا يأخذ السّاندوتش الآخر .
Now of course, development doesn't end at five.
الآن بالطّبع ، النّموّ لا ينتهي في الخامسة .
And we can see the continuation of this process
و يمكن أن نرى استمرار هذه العمليّة
of learning to think about other people's thoughts
لتّعلّم التّفكير في أفكار الناس الآخريين
by upping the ante
من خلال تصعيد الموقف
and asking children now, not for an action prediction,
و بسؤال الأطفال الآن ، ليس لغرض التنبّؤ ،
but for a moral judgment.
لكنّ لحكم أخلاقيّ .
So first I'm going to show you the three-year-old again.
أوّلا سأريكم الطفل البالغ من العمر ثلاثة سنوات ثانية .
RS.: So is Ivan being mean and naughty for taking Joshua's sandwich?
الفيديو : آر . إس . : كذلك هل إيفان يعتبر دنئ و مشاغب لأخذ ساندوتش جاشوا ؟
Child: Yeah.
الطّفل : نعم .
RS: Should Ivan get in trouble for taking Joshua's sandwich?
آر . إس . : هل يجب أن نأخذ إيفان في ورطة لأخذ ساندوتش جاشوا ؟
So it's maybe not surprising he thinks it was mean of Ivan
آر . إس . : لذا ربّما ليس مفاجئا أنه يعتقد أن إفان دنئ
to take Joshua's sandwich,
لأخذ ساندوتش جاشوا .
since he thinks Ivan only took Joshua's sandwich
بما أنه يعتقد أنّ إيفان قد أخذ ساندوتش جاشوا
to avoid having to eat his own dirty sandwich.
لتجنّب أكل ساندوتشه المتسخ الخاصّ به .
But now I'm going to show you the five-year-old.
لكنّ الآن سأريكم الطفل البالغ من العمر خمسة سنوات .
Remember the five-year-old completely understood
تذكّر الطفل البالغ من العمر خمسة سنوات فهم تمامًا
why Ivan took Joshua's sandwich.
لماذا إيفان أخذ ساندوتش جاشوا .
RS: Was Ivan being mean and naughty
فيديو : آر . إس . : هل إيفان يعتبر دنئ و مشاغب
for taking Joshua's sandwich?
لأخذ ساندوتش جاشوا ؟
Child: Um, yeah.
الطّفل : ام، نعم .
And so, it is not until age seven
آر . إس . : و لذا، ليس حتّى سنّ سبعة
that we get what looks more like an adult response.
حتى نحصل على إستجابه تبدو وكأنها إستجابة شخص بالغ .
RS: Should Ivan get in trouble for taking Joshua's sandwich?
الفيديو : آر . إس . : هل يجب أن نعاقب إيفان بسبب أخذ ساندوتش جاشوا ؟
Child: No, because the wind should get in trouble.
الطّفل : لا، لأنّ الرّيح هى التى لابد أن تكون في ورطة .
He says the wind should get in trouble
يقول ر.س. إنه يقول أنّ الرّيح ينبغي أن تكون في ورطة .
for switching the sandwiches.
لتحويل السّاندوتشات .
(Laughter)
( ضحك )
And now what we've started to do in my lab
و الآن ما قد بدأنا أن نعمله في معملي
is to put children into the brain scanner
هو وضع الأطفال في جهاز أشعّة لمسح المخّ
and ask what's going on in their brain
ونسأل ماذا يحدث في مخّهم
as they develop this ability to think about other people's thoughts.
بينما يُطوّرون هذه القدرة للتّفكير في أفكار الأشخاص الآخريين .
So the first thing is that in children we see this same brain region, the Right TPJ,
لذا الشّيء الأوّل هو أنّ في الأطفال نحن نرى نفس منطقة المخّ هذه ، آر تي بي جيه،
being used while children are thinking about other people.
هو مُستخدم بينما يفكّر الأطفال في النّاس الآخرين .
But it's not quite like the adult brain.
لكنّه ليس إلى حدّ ما يشابه عقل البالغ .
So whereas in the adults, as I told you,
لذا كما في البالغين ، كما أخبرتكم ،
this brain region is almost completely specialized --
منطقة المخّ هذه تقريبًا متخصّصة تمامًا .
it does almost nothing else except for thinking about other people's thoughts --
تقريبًا إنها لا تعمل شيئ آخر ، باستثناء التّفكير في أفكار النّاس الأخرى .
in children it's much less so,
في الأطفال هو أقلّ كثيرًا لذا ،
when they are age five to eight,
عندما يكونوا فى سنّ خمسة إلى ثمانية ،
the age range of the children I just showed you.
عمر الأطفال الذي أريتكم إياه الآن .
And actually if we even look at eight to 11-year-olds,
و في الواقع إذا نظرنا من سن الثّمانية حتّى الحادية عشر ،
getting into early adolescence,
دخول المراهقة المبكّرة ،
they still don't have quite an adult-like brain region.
لا يزالوا ليس لديهم منطقة مخ مشابهه أو مماثلة للبالغ .
And so, what we can see is that over the course of childhood
و لذا، ما يمكن أن نراه أنّه في أثناء الطفولة
and even into adolescence,
و حتّى في المراهقة،
both the cognitive system,
كلا من النّظام المعرفيّ ،
our mind's ability to think about other minds,
قدرة العقل فى التّفكير في العقول الأخرى ,
and the brain system that supports it
و نظام المخّ الّذي يسانده ،
are continuing, slowly, to develop.
يستمروا معاً ، ببطء، فى التّطوّر .
But of course, as you're probably aware,
لكنّ بالطّبع، كما أعتقد أنكم مدركون ،
even in adulthood,
حتّى في البلوغ ،
people differ from one another in how good they are
يختلف النّاس عن بعضهم البعض في كم هم جيّدون
at thinking of other minds, how often they do it
في تفكير فى العقول الأخرى ، كم مرّة يعملونه ،
and how accurately.
و ماهية دقته .
And so what we wanted to know was, could differences among adults
و لذا ما أردنا أن نعرفه كان ، استطيع الاختلافات بين البالغين ،
in how they think about other people's thoughts
في كيفية تفكيرهم في أفكار الناس الآخريين
be explained in terms of differences in this brain region?
يمكن أن تُشرح فيما يخصّ الاختلافات في هذه المنطقة المخّيه .
So, the first thing that we did is we gave adults a version
لذا الشّيء الأوّل الّذي فعلناه هو أننا أعطينا بالغين نسخة
of the pirate problem that we gave to the kids.
من مشكلة القرصان الّتي أعطيناها للأطفال .
And I'm going to give that to you now.
و أنا سأعطيكم ذلك الآن .
So Grace and her friend are on a tour of a chemical factory,
اذاً جراس و صديقها على جولة فى مصنع كيميائيّ
and they take a break for coffee.
و يأخذون راحةً للقهوة .
And Grace's friend asks for some sugar in her coffee.
و صديقة جراس تطلب بعض السّكّر في قهوتها .
Grace goes to make the coffee
تذهب جريس لعمل القهوة
and finds by the coffee a pot
و يجد بجانب القهوة إبريق
containing a white powder, which is sugar.
يحتوى على مسحوق أبيض الّذي هو سّكّر .
But the powder is labeled "Deadly Poison,"
لكنّ المسحوق عليه عنوان "سمّ مميت" .
so Grace thinks that the powder is a deadly poison.
لذا جراس تعتقد أن المسحوق هو سمّ مميت .
And she puts it in her friend's coffee.
و تضعه في قهوة صديقها .
And her friend drinks the coffee, and is fine.
و صديقتها تشرب القهوة ، وتجدها جيدة .
How many people think it was morally permissible
كمّ واحد منكم يعتقد أنّه كان مسموحًا أخلاقيًّا
for Grace to put the powder in the coffee?
لجراس أن تضع المسحوق في القهوة ؟
Okay. Good. (Laughter)
أوك . جيّدًا . (ضّحك)
So we ask people, how much should Grace be blamed
لذا نسأل الناس أيجب أن نلوم جراس
in this case, which we call a failed attempt to harm?
في هذه الحالة، الّتي نسمّيها محاولة فاشلة للضّرر .
And we can compare that to another case,
و يمكن أن نقارن ذلك إلى حالة أخرى
where everything in the real world is the same.
حيث كل شيئ في العالم الحقيقيّ هو نفس الشيء .
The powder is still sugar, but what's different is what Grace thinks.
المسحوق مازال السّكّر، لكنّ ما هو مختلف هو ما جريس يفكّر .
Now she thinks the powder is sugar.
الآن تعتقد أنّ المسحوق هو السّكّر .
And perhaps unsurprisingly, if Grace thinks the powder is sugar
و ربّما بشكل غير مفاجئ، إذا اعتقد جريس أنّ المسحوق هو السّكّر
and puts it in her friend's coffee,
و يضعه في قهوة صديقها،
people say she deserves no blame at all.
يقول النّاس أنها لا تستحقّ أيّ لوم على الإطلاق .
Whereas if she thinks the powder was poison, even though it's really sugar,
بينما إذا اعتقدت أنّ المسحوق كان سمّ، بالرّغم من أنه فعلاً سكّر،
now people say she deserves a lot of blame,
الآن النّاس يقولون أنها تستحقّ الكثير من اللّوم،
even though what happened in the real world was exactly the same.
بالرّغم من أنّ ما حدث في العالم الحقيقيّ كان نفس الشيء بالضّبط .
And in fact, they say she deserves more blame
و في الحقيقة يقولون أنها تستحقّ لوم أكثر
in this case, the failed attempt to harm,
في هذه الحالة، المحاولة الفاشلة للضّرر،
than in another case,
عن الحالة الأخرى،
which we call an accident.
التي نسميها حادثًا .
Where Grace thought the powder was sugar,
حيث اعتقدت غريس أنّ المسحوق كان السّكّر،
because it was labeled "sugar" and by the coffee machine,
لأنه عُلِّمَ السّكّر و بماكينة القهوة،
but actually the powder was poison.
لكنّ في الواقع كان المسحوق سمًّا .
So even though when the powder was poison,
لذا بالرّغم من أنّ عندما كان المسحوق سمًّا،
the friend drank the coffee and died,
شرب الصّديق القهوة و مات،
people say Grace deserves less blame in that case,
يقول النّاس أنّ جريس تستحقّ لوماً أقلّ في تلك الحالة،
when she innocently thought it was sugar,
عندما ببراءة اعتقدت أنّه كان السّكّر ،
than in the other case, where she thought it was poison
من في الحادث الآخر، حيث اعتقدت أنّه كان سمّ،
and no harm occurred.
و لم يحدث أذًى .
People, though, disagree a little bit
النّاس، مع ذلك، يختلفون بعض الشّيء
about exactly how much blame Grace should get
حول كمّ من اللوم بالضبط ينبغي أن يصل جريس
in the accident case.
في حالة الحادث .
Some people think she should deserve more blame,
يعتقد بعض النّاس أنها ينبغي أن تستحقّ لوم أكثر،
and other people less.
و آخرون يعتقدون لوم أقلّ .
And what I'm going to show you is what happened when we look inside
و ما سأعرضه عليكم هو ما حدث عندما ننظر بدّاخل
the brains of people while they're making that judgment.
أمخاخ الناس بينما يعملون تلك الأحكام .
So what I'm showing you, from left to right,
لذا ما أعرضه عليكم ، من اليسار إلى أيمن،
is how much activity there was in this brain region,
هو كمّ كان هناك من النشاط هذا الجزء من المخّ.
and from top to bottom, how much blame
ومن أعلى لأسفل، كمّ اللوم
people said that Grace deserved.
الذي قال النّاس أن جريس تستحقّه .
And what you can see is, on the left
و ما يمكن أن تراه هو، على اليسار
when there was very little activity in this brain region,
عندما هناك نشاط صغير جدًّا في هذه المنطقة من المخّ ،
people paid little attention to her innocent belief
أسترعى النّاس قليل من الإنتباه على ظنهم ببرائتها
and said she deserved a lot of blame for the accident.
و قالوا أنها استحقّت الكثير من اللّوم على الحادث .
Whereas on the right, where there was a lot of activity,
بينما، على اليمين ، حيث كان هناك الكثير من النّشاط،
people paid a lot more attention to her innocent belief,
أسترعى الناس الكثير من الإنتباه على ظنهم ببرائتها ،
and said she deserved a lot less blame
و قالوا أنها استحقّت لوماً أقل بكثير
for causing the accident.
لتسبيب الحادث .
So that's good, but of course
إذاً ذلك جيّد، لكنّ بالطّبع
what we'd rather is have a way to interfere
ما نفضّله هو أخذ طريقة للتداخل
with function in this brain region,
مع الوظيفة في هذه المنطقة من المخّ ،
and see if we could change people's moral judgment.
و نرى إذا يمكن أن نغيّر حكم النّاس الأخلاقيّ .
And we do have such a tool.
و فعلاً لدينا مثل هذه الأداة .
It's called Trans-Cranial Magnetic Stimulation,
إنه يُسَمَّى تنشيط ترانس-كرانيال المغنطيسيّ،
or TMS.
أو تي إم إس .
This is a tool that lets us pass a magnetic pulse
هذه الأداة تسمح لنا بتمرير إشارة مغنطيسيّة
through somebody's skull, into a small region of their brain,
عبر جمجمة الشّخص، في منطقة صغيرة لمخّهم،
and temporarily disorganize the function of the neurons in that region.
و مؤقّتًا يربك وظيفة الخلايا العصبيّة في تلك المنطقة .
So I'm going to show you a demo of this.
إذاً سأقوم بعرض تمهيدي لهذا.
First, I'm going to show you that this is a magnetic pulse.
أوّلاً سأعرض لكم ، أن هذه إشارة مغنطيسيّة،
I'm going to show you what happens when you put a quarter on the machine.
سأعرض لكم ما يحدث عندما تضع ربعًا على الماكينة .
When you hear clicks, we're turning the machine on.
عندما تسمع النّقرات نشغّل الماكينة .
So now I'm going to apply that same pulse to my brain,
الآن جدًّا أنا سأستعمل نفس ذلك النّبض في مخّي،
to the part of my brain that controls my hand.
إلى جزء من مخّي الّذي يتحكّم في يديّ .
So there is no physical force, just a magnetic pulse.
جدًّا ليس هناك قوّة بدنيّة، فقط نبض مغنطيسيّ .
Woman (Video): Ready, Rebecca? RS: Yes.
الفيديو : المرأة : جاهز ؟ ربيكا ساكس : نعم .
Okay, so it causes a small involuntary contraction in my hand
حسناً، لذا يسبّب طلقًا صغيرًا لا إراديّ في يدي
by putting a magnetic pulse in my brain.
بوضع نبض مغنطيسيّ في مخّي .
And we can use that same pulse,
و يمكن أن نستخدم نفس ذلك النّبض،
now applied to the RTPJ,
الآن قدّم طلبًا لآر تي بي جيه،
to ask if we can change people's moral judgments.
لسؤال إذا يمكن أن نغيّر أحكام النّاس الأخلاقيّة .
So these are the judgments I showed you before, people's normal moral judgments.
لذا هذه هي التّقديرات التي عرضها سابقاً ، تقديرات الناس الأخلاقيّة العاديّة .
And then we can apply TMS to the RTPJ
ثمّ يمكننا أن نستعمل تي إم إس في آر تي بي جيه
and ask how people's judgments change.
و نسأل كيف تتغير تقديرات النّاس .
And the first thing is, people can still do this task overall.
و الشّيء الأوّل،ما يزال بإمكان النّاس فعل هذه المهمة كليةً.
So their judgments of the case when everything was fine
لذا فتقديراتهم للحالة عندما كان كل شيئ جيّدًا
remain the same. They say she deserves no blame.
ظلّت نفس الشيء . يقولون أنها لا تستحقّ أيّ لوم .
But in the case of a failed attempt to harm,
لكنّ في قضيّة المحاولة الفاشلة للضّرر،
where Grace thought that it was poison, although it was really sugar,
حيث اعتقدت جريس أنّه كان سمّ،بالرّغم من أنه كان سكّر فعلاً،
people now say it was more okay, she deserves less blame
يقول النّاس أنّه كان أحسن الآن،
for putting the powder in the coffee.
تستحقّ أقلّ يلوم لوضع المسحوق في القهوة .
And in the case of the accident, where she thought that it was sugar,
و في حالة الحادث، حيث اعتقدت أنّه كان السّكّر،
but it was really poison and so she caused a death,
لكنّه فعلاً كان سمّ و لذا سبّبت موتًا،
people say that it was less okay, she deserves more blame.
يقول النّاس أنّه كان أقلّ حسنًا، تستحقّ لوم أكثر .
So what I've told you today is that
اذاً ما قد أخبرتكم به اليوم هو أن
people come, actually, especially well equipped
الناس يأتون ، في الواقع، بخاصّة مجهزين جيّدًا
to think about other people's thoughts.
للتّفكير في أفكار الآخرين .
We have a special brain system
لدينا نظام مخّ خاصّ
that lets us think about what other people are thinking.
الذي يسمح لنا بأن نفكّر بما يفكّر به الآخرين.
This system takes a long time to develop,
يستغرق هذا النّظام وقتاً طّويلاً للتّطوّر،
slowly throughout the course of childhood and into early adolescence.
ببطء خلال فترة الطفولة، و في بواكير المراهقة.
And even in adulthood, differences in this brain region
و حتّى في البلوغ، الاختلافات في هذه المنطقة من المخّ
can explain differences among adults
يمكن أن تشرح الاختلافات بين البالغين
in how we think about and judge other people.
في كيف نفكّر تقريبًا و نحكم على الآخرين.
But I want to give the last word back to the novelists,
لكننيّ أريد إعادة الكلمة النّهائيّة للرّوائيّين .
and to Philip Roth, who ended by saying,
و إلى فيليب روث الّذي انتهى بالقول،
"The fact remains that getting people right
"تبقى الحقيقة فهم النّاس ذلك بطريقة صحيحة
is not what living is all about anyway.
ليس هو كل شئ عن الحياة بأيّة حال .
It's getting them wrong that is living.
إساءة فهمهم هي الحياة.
Getting them wrong and wrong and wrong,
إساءة فهمهم و الخطأ و الخطأو الخطأ،
and then on careful reconsideration,
ثمّ في إعادة نظر متأنية،
getting them wrong again."
إساءة فهمهم مجدداً ".
Thank you.
شكرًا لكم .
(Applause)
( تصفيق )
Chris Anderson: So, I have a question. When you start talking about using
كريس أندرسون : عندما تبدأين في التّكلّم حول استخدام
magnetic pulses to change people's moral judgments,
النّبض المغنطيسيّ لتغيير أحكام النّاس الأخلاقيّة،
that sounds alarming.
ذلك يبدو مفزعًا .
(Laughter)
( ضحك )
Please tell me that you're not taking phone calls from the Pentagon, say.
من فضلك أخبريني أنّك لا تستقبلين مكالمات هاتفية من البنتاغون، مثلاً .
RS: I'm not.
ربيكا ساكس : لا أفعل .
I mean, they're calling, but I'm not taking the call.
أقصد، إنهم يتصلون ، لكننيّ لا أرد على المكالمة .
(Laughter)
( ضحك )
CA: They really are calling?
سي . إيه . : هل يتصلون فعلاً ؟
So then seriously,
إذا، ثمّ بشكل خطير، ثمّ بشكل خطير،
you must lie awake at night sometimes
يجب أن تستلقي مستيقظًة ليلاً أحيانًا
wondering where this work leads.
تتسائلين أين سيقود هذا العمل .
I mean, you're clearly an incredible human being,
أعني أنّك حقاً إنسانة غير معقولة.
but someone could take this knowledge
لكنّ شخص ما يمكن أن يأخذ هذه المعرفة
and in some future
و في وقت من المستقبل
not-torture chamber,
ليس غرفة تعذيب،
do acts that people here might be worried about.
يقوم بأفعال ربما يقلق منها بعض الناس هنا.
RS: Yeah, we worry about this.
آر . إس . : نعم، نحن نقلق على هذا .
So, there's a couple of things to say about TMS.
لذا، هناك شيئان للقول عن تي إم إس .
One is that you can't be TMSed without knowing it.
واحد هو أنك لا يمكن أن تستفيد منه بدون معرفته .
So it's not a surreptitious technology.
لذا فانها ليس تكنولوجيا سرّيّةً .
It's quite hard, actually, to get those very small changes.
إنّه إلى حدّ ما صعب في الواقع أن تحصل على تلك التّغييرات الصّغيرة جدًّا .
The changes I showed you are impressive to me
التّغييرات التي عرضتها عليكم هي رائعة بالنسبة لي
because of what they tell us about the function of the brain,
بسبب ما يخبرونا عن وظيفة المخّ .
but they're small on the scale
لكنهم صغار على مقياس
of the moral judgments that we actually make.
الأحكام الأخلاقية التي نصدرها في الواقع .
And what we changed was not people's
و ما غيّرناه لم يكن الأحكام
moral judgments when they're deciding what to do,
الأخلاقيّة للناس عندما يقرّرون ماذا يفعلون،
when they're making action choices.
عندما يقومون باتخاذ أفعال اختيارية .
We changed their ability to judge other people's actions.
نغيّر مقدرتهم للحكم على أفعال الآخرين.
And so, I think of what I'm doing not so much as
و لذا أفكّر فيما أعمله ليس كثير من ك
studying the defendant in a criminal trial,
دراسة المدّعى عليه في محاكمة جنائيّة،
but studying the jury.
لكنّ دراسة هيئة المحلّفين .
CA: Is your work going to lead to any recommendations
سي . إيه . : هل يؤدي عملك لأي نوع من التوصيات
in education, to perhaps bring up
في التّعليم، ربّما لجلب
a generation of kids able to make fairer moral judgments?
جيل من الأطفال قادر على عمل تقديرات أخلاقيّة عادلة ؟
RS: That's one of the idealistic hopes.
آر . إس . : تلك هي أحد الآمال المثاليّة .
The whole research program here of studying
برنامج البحث بالكامل هنا، للدّراسة
the distinctive parts of the human brain is brand new.
الأجزاء المميّزة للمخّ البشريّ، جديدة كلياً .
Until recently, what we knew about the brain
حتّى وقت قريب ما عرفناه عن المخّ
were the things that any other animal's brain could do too,
كانت الأشياء التي بمستطاع مخ أي حيوان آخر فعلها أيضاً.
so we could study it in animal models.
لذا يمكن أن ندرسه في نماذج الحيوان .
We knew how brains see, and how they control the body
عرفنا كيف ترى الأمخاخ ، و كيف يتحكّمون في الجسم،
and how they hear and sense.
و كيف يسمعون و يشعرون .
And the whole project of understanding
و مشروع الفهم بالكامل
how brains do the uniquely human things --
كيف تفعل الأمخاخ الأشياء البشريّة بشكل فريد،
learn language and abstract concepts,
تعلّم اللّغة، و المفاهيم المجرّدة،
and thinking about other people's thoughts -- that's brand new.
و التّفكير في أفكار النّاس الأخرى ، ذلك جديد كلياً.
And we don't know yet what the implications will be
و لا نعرف بعد، ماذا ستكون العواقب
of understanding it.
من فهمه.
CA: So I've got one last question. There is this thing called
سي . إيه . : إذا لديّ سؤال أخير . هناك يُسَمَّى
the hard problem of consciousness,
المسألة الصّعبة للوعي،
that puzzles a lot of people.
ذلك يحيّر الكثير من النّاس .
The notion that you can understand
المفهوم الذي يمكنك فهمه
why a brain works, perhaps.
لماذا يشتغل المخّ ، ربّما .
But why does anyone have to feel anything?
لكنّ لماذا يجب على أي شخص أن يشعر بأي شيئ ؟
Why does it seem to require these beings who sense things
ما الذي يبدو مطلوباً لتلك الأشياء التي تشعر بالأشياء
for us to operate?
بالنسبة لنا لتشتغل؟
You're a brilliant young neuroscientist.
أنت متخصّصة في علوم الجهاز العصبيّ صغيرة وذكيّة.
I mean, what chances do you think there are
أقصد، ما هي الفرص التي تعتقدين أنها هناك
that at some time in your career,
التي في وقت ما في مهنتك
someone, you or someone else,
شخص ما، أنت أو شخص ما آخر،
is going to come up with some paradigm shift
سيتوصّل إلى بعض التّحوّل الجذريّ
in understanding what seems an impossible problem?
في فهم ما يبدو مسألة مستحيلة .
RS: I hope they do. And I think they probably won't.
آر . إس . : آمل أن يستطيعوا . و أنا أعتقد أنه من المرجح لا.
CA: Why?
كريس: لماذا؟
RS: It's not called the hard problem of consciousness for nothing.
آر . إس . : إنها لا تُسَمَّى المشكلة الصّعبة للوعي دون مقابل .
(Laughter)
( ضحك )
CA: That's a great answer. Rebecca Saxe, thank you very much. That was fantastic.
سي . إيه . : تلك إجابة عظيمة . ربيكا ساكس، شكرًا جزيلاً . كان ذلك رائعًا .
(Applause)
( تصفيق )